A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Information Services, Archives and Records Retention, Office Files of Gloria Walters FA1729
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Information Services, Archives and Records Retention, Office Files of Gloria Walters
1973-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Walters, Gloria
FA1729
3.41 Cubic Feet 9 document boxes: 6 letter boxes; 2 legal boxes; and 1 half-letter box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files that Gloria Walters created when she served as Archivist/Records Retention Manager at the Ford Foundation and was based in the Foundation's Information Services, Archives and Records Retention unit. The collection is comprised of 3 series. The first series, Subject files, documents Walters' general activities in leading the Foundation's archives and records retention functions and supporting the larger Information Services department, primarily between 1993 and 1996, whereas the second series, Automation project files, specifically concerns the archive's automation project. Files in the third series, Researcher files, were removed from the Subject files series during processing and closed to access because of concerns over the privacy of the Foundation archive's researchers.
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, notes, drafts, reports, publications, meeting agendas, and charts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 in two different sets of records and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:111 and Accession 2019:112.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of three series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1973-1996
Series 2. Automation project files, 1990-1995
Series 3. Researcher files, 1986-1996
Ford Foundation; Archives; Records -- Management; Records retention; Information storage and retrieval systems; Cataloging
- Subject files, 1973-1996; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Gloria Walters' general activities for leading the Ford Foundation's archives and records retention unit and supporting the larger Information Services department are documented within this series. The files largely concern topics like archives and records retention policies and workflows, transfers of materials to the archive, communication with the Foundation's field offices, microfilming of archival materials, the Central Index for the Foundation's grant records, the automation project, and the archives and records retention unit's administration.
  Part of Walters' responsibilities for developing, disseminating, and enacting the Foundation's archives and records retention policies and workflows included introducing and reviewing the policies with Foundation staff and Program Officer orientations. The communication between the Foundation archive and field offices documented within the files primarily pertains to the transferring to the archive and microfilming of closed grant records. Regarding the archive's automation project, the series includes documentation of Walters' role in searching for a consultant to review the archive's holdings, descriptive data, systems, and procedures and to develop a plan for automation. Further information on the automation project can be found in the collection's second series.
  Walters' administrative responsibilities documented within the series include budgeting and gathering and submitting statistics for the archives and records retention unit. Statistics reports relating to archive researchers have been relocated to the end of the series and closed to access because of privacy concerns. Similarly, files pertaining to the archive's reference work with researchers were removed and processed into series 3 which is also restricted from access.
  - Archives - Accessions, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Archives and Records Retention Unit General Staff Meeting, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees records register and microfilming project, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dockets microfilming, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Central Index survey, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Deleted documents, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Information Services Quarterly Meeting, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lektriever maintenance agreements - Kardex, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Methylene Blue Test results - Microfilm, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Microfilm problem - Particle buildup, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Microfilm project, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grants Management System (GMS) survey, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Officers Meetings agendas, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Archives orientation - Elaine Kranich, Office of the Secretary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Services Project Status Reports, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Information Services projects updates, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Videotape Project, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Program Officer Orientation - Archives and Records Center, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Human Resources Staff Activity Report, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fiscal Year 1995 year end Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fiscal Year 1995 October-December Archives and Records Center statistics, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fiscal Year 1995 January-March Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fiscal Year 1995 April-June Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Fiscal Year 1995 July-August Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Brian Urquhart records transfer to United Nations, 1995 August 18 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Foundation archives public access survey, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Administrative Services handbook - Archives and Records Retention section, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Archives - Accessions, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Administrative Services Training Program, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Board of Trustees records microfilming project, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Internal audit - Records Retention, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 budget, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 budget - Year end projections, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Cataloging backlog, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Board of Trustees records microfilming project - Vendors, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Copyright, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence - Staff research requests, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence - Outside research requests, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Equipment survey and supplies, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Archives internships, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Information Services Quarterly Meeting, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Methylene Blue Test results - Microfilm, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - New York Times, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - OCLC, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Officers Meetings agendas, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Oral History Project - Opening transcripts, 1984-1994 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Archivists Round Table Workshop: Care of Photographs, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Program Officer assignments and Program Assistants, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Automation Project - SoftSolutions, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Information Services projects update, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Program Officer and Program Assistant Orientation, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Administrative Services Project Status Reports, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Records Center correspondence, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Recycling, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation records in other repositories - Archives policies and procedures, 1973-1994 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Staff departure checklist guidelines, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 January-March Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 October-December Archives and Records Center statistics, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 April-June Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 July-September Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Fiscal Year 1994 year end Archives and Records Center statistics, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Training sessions - OCLC/METRO, 1994 October 5 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Wang documents conversion, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Field Office - Cairo, Egypt, 1994 May 25 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Field Office - Dakar, Senegal, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Field Office - Dhaka, Bangladesh, 1994 January 19 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Field Office - New Delhi, India, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Field Office - Lagos, Nigeria, 1994 June 29 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Field Office - Mexico City, Mexico, 1994 March 21 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Field Office - Santiago, Chile, 1994 March (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Ford Foundation administrative calendars, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Archives - Reports and catalog records, circa 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Archives - Accessions, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Jack Goldman consultancy report, Phase 1, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Jack Goldman consultancy report, Phase 1 drafts, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Database management systems (DBMS) project - Request for proposals (RFPs), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Iron Mountain (IMAR) - Correspondence and trip report, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Library correspondence, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Meetings - Staff and weekly with Linda Feeney, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Micrographics - Draft forms, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Archives move, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Office procedure guidelines - drafts, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Organization charts - Archives and Records Retention Unit, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Program Officer Orientation, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Joint Program Review, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Program Officers Orientation Notebook revisions, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Archives Questionnaire - Program Officers, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Information Services projects updates, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Records Analyst position, 1987-1993 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Records Center correspondence, 1993 September 1 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Records Center projects - Surveys, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - SoftSolutions, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Archives and Records Retention Staff Meetings, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 July-September Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 April-June Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 5, Folder 113)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Statistics related to specific researchers has been relocated to the end of the series (Researcher statistics - Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 January-March Archives and Records Center statistics (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Paul Ylvisaker - Council on Foundations, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Field Offices, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Field Office - Bangkok, Thailand, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Field Office - Cairo, Egypt, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Field Office - Dakar, Senegal, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Field Office - Jakarta, Indonesia, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Field Office - Khartoum, Sudan, 1993 April 14 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Field Office - Lagos, Nigeria, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Field Office - Mexico City, Mexico, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Field Offices - Nairobi, Kenya and Harare, Zimbabwe, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Field Office - New Delhi, India, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Field Office - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Researcher statistics, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 149)
    Restricted - confidential material.
  - Researcher statistics, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Researcher statistics, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Researcher statistics, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Researcher statistics, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Researcher statistics, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Researcher statistics, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - Researcher statistics, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Researcher statistics, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - Researcher statistics, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Researcher statistics, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Researcher statistics, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 160)
- Automation project files, 1990-1995; 2
  Materials in this series document Ford Foundation Archives and Records Retention Manager Gloria Walter's work on the archive's automation project. They concern pre-automation tasks the Archives and Records Retention unit staff needed to perform, cataloging, databases, the grants records Central Index, and the Information Services department investigating and contracting different systems and software vendors for the automation project.
  - Advanced Media Group (AMG) final report, 1993 November 22 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Cataloging automation - Archives and Library task lists, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Archives automation, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Archives automation, Phase 2, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Automation training - Information Dimensions, Inc. (IDI) brochures, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Automation project - Background material, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 132-133)
  - Automation project - Information Dimensions, Inc. (IDI) printed materials, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 134-135)
  - BASISplus - Records management system requirements, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Grants Management System (GMS) survey - Archives' response, 1995 August 8 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Grants information - Information and Records Units (IR units), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Automation project - Pre-automation tasks, 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Automation project - Profiling and cataloging mapping, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 140-141)
  - Automation project - TECHLIBplus (TLP) test data questions and comments, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Cuadra STAR demo, 1990-1994 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Information Dimensions, Inc. (IDI) - Vendor information, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Automation project - MEREX, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - TECHLIBplus (TLP) manual - Training, 1991-1995 (Box 8, Folder 146-148)
- Researcher files, 1986-1996; 3
  Access to series is restricted.
  The files in this series document Gloria Walters' engagement with the reference operations of the Ford Foundation Archives and Records Retention unit mostly between 1993 and 1995. These materials were separated out from the rest of Walters' subject files in Series 1 and restricted from access because of privacy concerns pertaining to the researchers discussed in the documents.
  The series contains materials like reports, correspondence, articles, and agendas. These materials concern research requests, responses to requests, and summary information on researchers who visited the archives, including researcher name, purpose, affiliation, research topic, hours spent, and who on the archives staff assisted the researcher.
  - Reference highlights, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Reference meetings, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Reference - Pending outside researchers, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Researcher - Guliana Gemelli, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Researcher - Craig Hymowitz, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Researcher - Esme Bhan, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Researcher requests, 1994-1996 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Reference meetings, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Reference - Pending outside researchers, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Researcher requests, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Researcher - Lawrence Jarvick, 1986-1994 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Researcher - Enid Schoettle, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence - Researchers, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Reference highlights, 1989-1993 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Reference meetings and activities, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Reference - Central Index User Profile list, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 109)